<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="f-spot" lang="pt_BR">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>O Manual do F-Spot</title>
		<abstract role="description">
			<para>Este é o manual do usuário para F-Spot, um gerenciador de fotos pessoais do GNOME.</para>
		</abstract>
		<subtitle>Este é o manual do usuário para F-Spot, um gerenciador de fotos pessoais do GNOME.</subtitle>
		<copyright>
			<year>2007-2009</year>
			<holder>Aaron Bockover, Gabriel Burt, Miguel de Icaza, Bengt Thuree</holder>
		</copyright><copyright><year>2007</year><holder>Vladimir Melo (vladimirmelo@foresightlinux.org)</holder></copyright>
		<publisher>
			<publishername>Projeto de Documentação do GNOME</publishername>
		</publisher>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Miguel</firstname>
				<surname>de Icaza</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Aaron</firstname>
				<surname>Bockover</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Bengt</firstname>
				<surname>Thuree</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Gabriel</firstname>
				<surname>Burt</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Alexandre</firstname>
				<surname>Prokoudine</surname>
			</author>
			<author role="maintainer">
				<firstname>Stephane</firstname>
				<surname>Delcroix</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<!--<include href="legal.xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>-->
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
				<date>2008-09-25</date>
			</revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
				<date>2008-09-12</date>
			</revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
				<date>2007-07-26</date>
			</revision>
		 </revhistory>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="organizing">
		<title>Organizando suas fotos</title>
		
		<sect1 id="import">
			<title>Importar</title>

			<para>Você pode importar fotos de seu disco rígido ou de sua câmera. Quando importar suas fotos para o F-Spot de sua câmera, sempre será feita uma cópia delas, deixando você livre para limpar a memória de sua câmera. Por padrão, F-Spot fará uma cópia das fotos importadas de seu disco rígido. Desmarque a opção <guilabel>Copiar</guilabel> do diálogo de importação ou mantenha pressionado <keycap>Shift</keycap> ao arrastar as fotos para o F-Spot se não desejar copiá-las de seu disco rígido.</para>
			
			<para>
				By default, F-Spot copies your photos to the 
				<filename class="directory">~/Photos</filename> folder. You can change 
				the folder F-Spot uses in <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog 
				(<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>). You can also disable physical copying of images to that 
				directory and make F-Spot only reference to existing files. For that you 
				need to disable checkbox <guilabel>Copy files to the Photos folder</guilabel>. 
			</para>
			<para>
				If there is a tiny chance that some of your photos are already imported 
				from the chosen source, you can use <guilabel>Detect duplicates</guilabel> 
				option. In this case F-Spot will try to find out if exactly this image is 
				already present in the database and thus new copy of it should not be 
				imported. 
			</para>
			<para>
				If all the photos you are importing at one time are from a particular event, 
				or have some other characteristic in common, you can create a tag for them 
				so you can later find them with ease. To do this, follow the instructions from  
				<xref linkend="tag"/> to create a new tag, then when you are importing 
				them, check the button for <guilabel>Attach Tag</guilabel> and choose the 
				tag you created. 
			</para>
			
			<tip>
				<para>
					F-Spot uses a database stored at 
					<filename>~/.config/f-spot/photos.db</filename>. Note, to access it, use 
					the sqlite3 command. You can also manually specify path to a database by 
					running F-Spot with <option>-b</option> option.
				</para>
			</tip>
			
			<para>
				After an import, F-Spot will display the pictures of the latest import 
				roll only. Read <xref linkend="enjoying-search"/> to learn how to deal 
				with import rolls.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also import directly from Mozilla 
				<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/">Firefox</ulink> and 
				<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/thunderbird/">Thunderbird</ulink> using 
				<ulink url="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/7091">Firefox</ulink> 
				and <ulink url="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/thunderbird/addon/7011">Thunderbird</ulink> 
				F-Spot importer extensions written by 
				<ulink url="http://personalpages.tds.net/~cdovel/">Pizzach</ulink>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="edit">
			<title>Editar</title>
			
			<para>Se você der um clique duplo ou digitar enter sobre uma imagem, você acessará o modo Editar, onde pode remover olho vermelho, cortar, e ajustar brilho e cores.</para>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-versions">
				<title>Versões</title>
				
				<para>
					When you edit your photos, a new copy (called a version) is created, 
					so your original is never altered. After your first edit to a photo, subsequent 
					edits will modify the same version. If you want to create multiple versions 
					of your photo, perhaps with different cropping or coloring, you can do so 
					via the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Create new version</guimenuitem></menuchoice> option.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-crop">
				<title>Cortar</title>
				
				<para>
					Cropping an image is a great way to improve the quality of a photograph by 
					change how it is framed. You crop a photo by selecting the part of the photo 
					you want to keep. If you want your photo to be the exact dimensions necessary 
					for a certain print size, you can constrain the kind of selection F-Spot will allow 
					you to draw by choosing the appropriate size from the constraint drop down. 
					See the <xref linkend="edit-remove-red-eye"/> below for details on making 
					a selection on your photo.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Crop tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-crop.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>Uma vez que tenha feito sua seleção de corte, você deve clicar no botão cortar abaixo da imagem para finalizar o corte. Se você estiver trabalhando com a foto original, o corte cria uma nova versão da sua foto.</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-straighten">
				<title>Straighten</title>
				
				<para>
					Straighten effect is a tool to level a photo, quite helpful for landscapes 
					taken without a tripod, when (imaginary) line of horizon is not at 0°. 
					This tool rotates an image by a specified angle and automagically crops the 
					resulted image, so that you always see a perfect rectangle.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Straighten tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-straighten.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-adjust-colors">
				<title>Ajustar Cores</title>
				
				<para>
					To adjust the brightness, contrast, and colors of a photo, first click 
					the <guibutton>Adjust the photo colors</guibutton> icon to open the 
					adjustment dialog. Change then some settings and save them with 
					<guibutton>OK</guibutton>. 
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Adjust Colors tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-adjust-colors.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-auto-color">
				<title>AutoColor</title>
				
				<para>
					This effect automatically adjusts color levels to make a pretty balanced 
					picture color-wise. It serves best for pictures taken with automatical 
					white balance, when camera didn't manage to do the job well.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>AutoColor</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-autocolor.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-desaturate">
				<title>Desaturate</title>
				
				<para>
					To make a colorful photo a black and white one, open a photo of choice 
					and press <guibutton>Desaturate</guibutton> button.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Desaturation tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-desaturate.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-sepia">
				<title>Sepia</title>
				
				<para>
					To make a colorful photo look like an old-style picture in sepia tones, 
					open a photo of choice and press <guibutton>Sepia</guibutton> button.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Desaturation tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-sepia.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-remove-red-eye">
				<title>Remover Olhos Vermelhos</title>
				
				<para>
					To remove redeye from a photo, you need to select a zone containing 
					the eyes. You may want to zoom in on the image to accurately select 
					the eyes in the photo. You should be able to correct both eyes on the 
					same person in one shot, or even the eyes from multiple people at once. 
					If this doesn't work for you, or the selected zone contains some vivid 
					red parts (lips, ...) you'll probably have to correct one red eye at a time.
				</para>
				<para>Para fazer sua seleção, clique em um canto do retângulo que será sua seleção, e arraste seu mouse para o canto da diagonal e libere. Você pode redimensionar sua seleção arrastando suas bordas, ou movê-la clicando no centro e arrastando para onde quiser.</para>
				<para>
					Once you have selected a zone, you can remove the red from it by 
					clicking the red-eye button beneath the photo.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Red-Eye tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-red-eye.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<tip>
					<para>
						You can change the threshold for redeyes detection by changing 
						the gconf key 
						<filename class="directory">/apps/f-spot/edit/redeye_threshold</filename>.
					</para>
				</tip>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-soft-focus">
				<title>Soft Focus</title>
				
				<para>
					In photography sharpening one region of a picture, while blurring 
					all the rest, is a way to make an emphasis and grab attention. 
					It is achieved by using a lens that allows shooting with a short 
					distance in front of and beyond the subject that appears to be in 
					focus. Soft focus effect is a way to emulate such a lens.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Soft Focus tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-soft-focus.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>
					Click to choose central point of the area you want to be in focus 
					and adjust amount of blurring, then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-sharpen">
				<title>Sharpen</title>
				
				<para>
					Out-of-focus photographs and most digitized images often need a 
					sharpness correction. The Unsharp Mask effect sharpens edges of 
					the elements without increasing noise or blemish. To sharpen a 
					photo choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sharpen...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and specify the 
					following values:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">Amount</parameter> — strength of sharpening.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">Radius</parameter> — how many pixels on either 
							side of an edge will be affected by sharpening. High resolution images 
							allow higher radius.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">Threshold</parameter> — the minimum difference 
							in pixel values that indicates an edge where sharpen must be applied. 
							This helps avoiding creation of blemishes in face, sky or water surface.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-describe">
				<title>Descrever</title>
				
				<para>Você também pode colocar a descrição da imagem clicando na caixa de entrada de texto abaixo da imagem e digitando.</para>
				<para>Uma vez que tenha feito sua seleção de corte, você deve clicar no botão cortar abaixo da imagem para finalizar o corte. Se você estiver trabalhando com a foto original, o corte cria uma nova versão da sua foto.</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-adjust-time">
				<title>Adjust Time</title>
				
				<para>
					In both 'browse' or 'edit' modes, you can adjust the time of one 
					or multiple pictures (<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Adjust Time</guimenuitem></menuchoice>). Adjusting 
					the time of multiple pictures at once helps you shift all an import 
					roll if, e.g. the time on your camera is badly set or if you forgot 
					to change it according to DST.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="tag">
			<title>Etiqueta</title>
			<para>F-Spot lhe possibilita organizar e curtir suas fotos ao associá-las às várias etiquetas personalizáveis. Uma etiqueta é basicamente um rótulo. F-Spot vem com etiquetas padronizadas de início; você é livre para alterá-las e adicionar novas. Por exemplo, se você quiser criar uma etiqueta para um evento especifico, você pode criar uma etiqueta com o mesmo nome do evento na categoria Eventos.</para>
			<para>Existem várias formas de etiquetar fotos:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>arraste e solte a(s) foto(s) sobre a etiqueta</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>arraste e solte a etiqueta sobre a(s) foto(s)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>através do menu de contexto da foto</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>através dos menus Etiquetas e Editar</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						by typing them in. Press <keycap>t</keycap> to pop up the tag
						entry bar. Here you can enter the tags, separated by commas.
					</para>
					<para>
						You can also use auto-completion in this entry bar: After
						entering the beginning of a tag name, press
						<keycap>Tab</keycap> to see the first possible completion. You can
						cycle between other possible completions by pressing
						<keycap>Tab</keycap> again, and backwards with
						<keycombo action="simul"><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>.
						To confirm the suggested completion and enter a new tag, press
						<keycap>,</keycap>. By pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap> you
						leave the tag entry bar, possibly confirming the current
						completion. To abort the auto completion, just keep on typing.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>A primeira foto que você associar a uma etiqueta será usada para o ícone da etiqueta.Você pode sempre editar o nome da etiqueta, da etiqueta principal e do ícone através do menu de contexto escolhendo <guilabel>Editar etiqueta</guilabel>.</para>
			<para>Você pode alterar uma etiqueta principal arrastando-a e soltando-a onde desejar. Você pode também editar o nome da etiqueta selecionando-a e pressionando <keycap>F2</keycap>. Por último, se você tem o controle árvore de etiqueta ativo (por exemplo, acabou de clicar numa etiqueta), pode iniciar a digitar o nome de uma etiqueta, e todas as etiquetas expandidas na lista serão procuradas e você pulará para aquelas correspondentes.</para>
			
			<para>
				You can also change size of tag icons in the sidebar or even make tag 
				icons invisible by selecting preferred option from <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tag Icons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> 
				menu.
			</para>
			
			<tip>
				<para>
					F-Spot can write tags as metadata fields into JPEG files. Tags for 
					various RAW files, PNG, TIFF, and others are written to F-Spot's 
					database. You will have to re-tag these files if you re-import your 
					collection.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="enjoying">
		<title>Curtindo suas fotos</title>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-browse">
			<title>Navegar</title>
			<para>Você pode usar o controle deslizante para navegar pelas suas fotos por mês ou diretório. Para alterar essa configuração, vá em<menuchoice><guimenu>Ver</guimenu><guimenuitem>Ordenar por</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-search">
			<title>Pesquisar</title>
			
			<para>
				F-Spot uses search filters to help you better define search criteria.
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-tags">
				<title>Tags</title>
				
				<para>Você pode iniciar uma pesquisa dando um clique duplo ou ativando uma etiqueta da lista de etiquetas. Como alternativa, pode mostrar a barra de pesquisa com <menuchoice><guimenu>Localizar</guimenu><guimenuitem>Mostrar Barra de Pesquisa</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Com a barra de pesquisa exibida, você pode arrastar a etiqueta para a barra de pesquisa.</para>
				<para>Para localizar fotos que estejam marcadas por duas etiquetas, ative a primeira na exibição de etiqueta ou arraste-a para a barra de pesquisa, então arraste a segunda etiqueta e solte-a sobre a primeira. Você pode também usar o menu de contexto da segunda etiqueta na exibição de etiqueta, ou usar o menu <guimenu>Localizar</guimenu>, e escolher <guimenuitem>Localizar Com...</guimenuitem> e selecionar a primeira etiqueta (ou grupo de etiquetas).</para>
				<para>Você pode arrastar o ícone da etiqueta na barra de pesquisa para alterar de encontrando por essa e outra etiqueta para encontrando por essa ou outra etiqueta.</para>
				<para>Você pode procurar por fotos que não tenham uma etiqueta específica ao dar um clique duplo na etiqueta na barra de pesquisa. Como alternativa, pode abrir o menu de contexto da etiqueta na barra de pesquisa e selecionar <guimenuitem>Excluir</guimenuitem>.</para>
				<para>Para remover a etiqueta da barra de pesquisa, arraste-a para fora da barra de pesquisa, ou vá ao menu de contexto e selecione <guimenuitem>Remover</guimenuitem>.</para>
				<para>Por padrão, fotos etiquetadas como <emphasis>Ocultas</emphasis> não serão mostradas. Você deve incluir explicitamente a etiqueta <emphasis>Ocultas</emphasis> em sua pesquisa para mostrar essas fotos.</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-import-rolls">
				<title>Import Rolls</title>
				<para>
					F-Spot remembers what pictures were imported every now and then. Use 
					<menuchoice><guimenu>Find</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Last import roll</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to limit search 
					to last importing session or use <menuchoice><guimenu>Find</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Select Import Rolls...</guimenuitem>
					</menuchoice> to make a finer selection of imported photos:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">At</parameter> — to select photos from a particular importing session
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">After</parameter> — to select all photos imported begining with a particular importing session
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class="option">Between</parameter> — to select all photos imported between two particular importing sessions
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					Every time you change settings of the filter, the amount of selected photos 
					will appear in the bottom part of the dialog.
				</para>
				<para>
					When you apply Import Roll filter, in the Find bar you will see 
					<guilabel>Find: Import Roll</guilabel>. Now you can add some other 
					filter to finetune your selection.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you don't need the Import Roll filter anymore, choose <menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Find</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Clear roll filter</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to remove 
					Import Roll from search criteria. You can also click the close button 
					(<guibutton>X</guibutton>) of the search bar to discard all the current 
					search options.
				</para>
				<tip>
					<para>
						The number of displayed rolls in the dialog is defined by the gconf key 
						<filename class="directory">/apps/f-spot/import/gui_roll_history</filename>. 
						Default value is 10.
					</para>
				</tip>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-type-to-find">
				<title>Type-to-find</title>
				<para>Existe também uma entrada digite-para-localizar. Pressione <keycap>/</keycap> para abri-la. Não é possível usar ao mesmo tempo como barra de localização. Você pode digitar consultas como "EtiquetaA e (EtiquetaB ou (EtiquetaC e EtiquetaD))". Em qualquer ponto, se F-Spot reconhecer o que você digitou como uma consulta válida, irá atualizar sua pesquisa. Ainda não há suporte para o operador <emphasis>não</emphasis>.</para>
				
				<para>
					This function will also search for the typed text into photos comments and filename.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="enjoying-fullscreen-mode-and-slideshows">
			<title>Modo Tela Cheia e Apresentação de Slide</title>
			<para>Para menos distrações e maior exibição, você pode ver suas fotos em modo tela cheia. Você controla quando mostrar a próxima foto ou retornar à anterior. Entre em modo tela cheia pressionando <keycap>F11</keycap> a qualquer hora ou pressionando o botão na barra de ferramentas.</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Tela Cheia</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-fullscreen.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>No modo apresentação de slides, você pode se acomodar e ver suas fotos como se elas fossem apresentadas para você. Pode iniciar a apresentação ao apertar o botão na barra de ferramentas.</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Apresentação de Slide</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-slideshow.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="sharing">
		<title>Compartilhando suas fotos</title>
		
		<abstract>
			<para>Existem muitas formas de compartilhar suas fotos usando F-Spot. Todos os métodos a seguir compartilharão apenas as fotos selecionadas quando forem executados.</para>
		</abstract>
		
		<sect1 id="sharing-e-mail">
			<title>E-mail</title>
			<para>Enviar por e-mail suas fotos diretamente do F-Spot com o menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Arquivo</guimenu><guimenuitem>Enviar E-mail</guimenuitem></menuchoice> .</para>
			<note>
				<title>Note 1</title>
				<para>
					The email program used for this is defined at the GNOME level. 
					You can change the default e-mailer for your user using the 
					<application>Preferred Applications</application> tool in 
					<menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<note>
				<title>Note 2</title>
				<para>
					If some of the photos you'd like to send by email are in a format 
					that F-Spot can't write (e.g. RAW images), the size selection dialog 
					will become insensitive and the originals will be sent.
				</para>
			</note>
			<tip>
				<para>
					If you're sending resized pictures, F-Spot will keep the modified versions 
					somewhere in the <filename class="directory">/tmp</filename> directory for 
					30 seconds. It's not an issue with evolution, which makes it's own local 
					copy of the attachments, but could be a bit shorter if you're using Thunderbird. 
					You can change the delay by editing the gconf key 
					<filename class="directory">/apps/f-spot/export/email/delete_timeout_seconds</filename>.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-print">
			<title>Imprimir</title>
			<para>Imprimir suas fotos com o menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Arquivo</guimenu><guimenuitem>Imprimir</guimenuitem></menuchoice> .</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-burn-to-cd">
			<title>Gravar para CD</title>
			<para>
				Burn your photos to CD or DVD with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Export</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Export to CD</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> menu.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="website-gallery-folder">
			<title>Gerar uma Galeria Online ou Pasta</title>
			<para>O recurso <menuchoice><guimenu>Arquivo</guimenu><guimenuitem>Exportar</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Exportar para Pasta</guimenuitem></menuchoice> lhe permite três maneiras de exportar suas imagens.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><guilabel>Usar Original</guilabel> exporta suas fotos prontas para serem usadas com o software livre <ulink url="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/original.php"> Original Photo Gallery</ulink> de Jakub Steiner. Se não estiver certo desta opção, provavelmente não é a apropriada para você.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><guilabel>Usar arquivos HTML estáticos</guilabel> exporta suas fotos para um site interativo, pronto para você enviar.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><guilabel>Arquivos Simples</guilabel> exporta suas imagens como arquivos para dentro de diretórios, sem colocá-las em uma galeria.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-flickr-or-php-gallery">
			<title>Post to your online galleries</title>
			<para>
				If you use Flickr, SmugMug, 23hq, Tabblo, Facebook, Zooomr or Picasa Web Album, you can post your files 
				directly from F-Spot with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Export</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu, choosing corresponding submenu item.
			</para>
			<para>Se você usa o programa PHP conhecido como <ulink url="http://gallery.sourceforge.net/"> Gallery</ulink>, você pode postar suas fotos para um álbum existente com o menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Arquivo</guimenu><guimenuitem>Exportar</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Exportar para Galeria Online</guimenuitem></menuchoice> . Você deve primeiro habilitar o módulo Remoto dentro de sua instalação do Gallery.</para>
			<note>
				<title>Note for Gallery 2.2 users</title>
				<para>
					The Remote plugin for Gallery should be 1.0.8 or newer.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				<ulink url="http://pennave.sourceforge.net">PennAve</ulink> is a Python 
				web-application that directly uses F-Spot's database to present a dynamic 
				gallery of your photos and tags.
			</para>
			<para>
				<ulink url="http://www.conduit-project.org">Conduit</ulink> is an application 
				that can sync photos that have a particular tag with your Flickr or Picasa 
				Web Album web storage.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="cms">
		<title>Color management</title>

		<sect1 id="cms-what-is-cms">
			<title>What's color management</title>
			
			<para>
				When you capture a photo and look at it on a display, it looks different than 
				on a camera's preview display or on any other display. It will also look 
				different when you print it. This is because every device has unique color 
				reproduction capabilities.
			</para>

			<para>
				Color management system (CMS) is a tool to achieve reliable color reproduction 
				for both display and output (e.g. a printer). A CMS relies on color profiles 
				to map original colors to the color that a device can reproduce so that colors 
				will appear the same way everywhere — on a computer LCD monitor, on a print 
				from your local photolab etc.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-what-is-icc-profile">
			<title>What's a color profile</title>
			
			<para>
				A color profile is a file with either .icc (thus its is often called an ICC 
				profile) or .icm extension that describes how device's colors correspond to a 
				universal description of colors.
			</para>

			<para>
				There are several types of profiles: 
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Input device profile. It's profile for a camera or a profile that an 
						application like XSane embeds into a scanned image. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Working space profile. It's a profile that describes color space in 
						which all operations are done inside an application. Usually very wide 
						gamut profiles like AdobeRGB1998 or ProPhotoRGB are used for that.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Display profile. It's a profile for a monitor. 
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Output profile. This is usually a profile for you printer. 
					</para>				
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>					

			<para>
				Currently F-Spot allows setting only display and output profiles. 
				All color operations are done in sRGB color space. 
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-how-to-get-icc-profile">
			<title>How to get my screen/printer color profile </title>

			<para>
				There are few ways to get a color profile. 
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-cd-or-internet">
				<title> From CD or Internet </title>

				<para>
					Many hardware manufacturers put color profiles into CD in the bundle. 
					If you have one (from monitor or printer), you can use it. Or you can 
					download it from the Internet (usually, from support section of the 
					manufacturer's web site). Some camera manufacturers (Nikon, Canon) 
					also provide ICC profiles.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-calibrating-and-profiling">
				<title>Calibrating and profiling</title>

				<para>
					Best results can be achieved by calibrating and profiling devices with 
					a measurement device. It is not so difficult, but it means that you need 
					a spectrophotometer to do all measurements and create an ICC profile.
				</para>

				<para>
					If you are on Windows or Mac OS X, you can use manufacturer's software 
					coming with a spectrophotometer. On Linux you will have to use either 
					<ulink url="http://www.argyllcms.com">Argyll</ulink>, which is a set of 
					versatile command line tools, or 
					<ulink url="http://lprof.sourceforge.net/">LProf</ulink>, which has a 
					graphical user interface. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Please refer to documentation of third party hardware and software 
					vendors for details.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-embedding">
				<title>Embedding</title>

				<para>
					Image formats themselves (such as TIFF, JPEG, PNG...) may contain embedded 
					color profiles. If color management is enabled, F-Spot looks for such 
					embedded profiles and takes them into consideration.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-how-to-use">
			<title>How to use color management in F-Spot</title>
			
			<para>
				Color management in F-Spot can use only RGB profiles at this time 
				(and you can't see other profiles in the F-Spot).
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Copy your color profiles into the 
						<filename class="directory">/usr/share/color/icc</filename> or 
						<filename class="directory">/usr/local/share/color/icc</filename> 
						directory.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Enable the color management with the <menuchoice>
						<guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice> menu.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Select <guilabel>Display</guilabel> and <guilabel>Output</guilabel> 
						profiles.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>					

			<tip>
				<para>
					You can use <ulink url="http://burtonini.com/blog/computers/xicc">xicc</ulink> 
					to load ICC profile to display and use the loaded profile from F-Spot. 
					Just mark the checkbox <guilabel>Try to use the system display 
					profile</guilabel>.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="extend">
		<title>Extend functionality</title>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-what-extensions-are">
			<title>What extensions are</title>

			<para>
				F-Spot extensions are means to add new functionality to the application. 
				F-Spot supports two types of extension: exporters (which allow exporting 
				photos to new web services or data storages) and tools (which allow new 
				ways of color correction, duplicate photos finders etc.). Extensions are 
				distributed in form of extension packages.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the best traditions of not reinventing the wheel extensions can use other 
				extensions, which means that one extension cannot work, if another extension 
				is not installed. This concept of dependance actually means that
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you cannot install an extension, if the extension it depends on, is not present in the system
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you cannot remove an extension on which some other extension depends
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-managing-extensions">
			<title>Managing extensions</title>
			
			<para>
				To manage extensions choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Manage Extensions</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item.
			</para>

			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-managing-extension-repositories">
				<title>Managing extension repositories</title>

				<para>
					Simply put, repositories are extension storages. They can be either network 
					or local. To add a new repository click Repositories button, choose type of 
					the repository you are about to add and provide either URL or path. If the URL 
					or path you specified doesn't contain a description (index) file for extensions, 
					a warning message will pop up to tell you that.
				</para>
				<para>
					To remove a repository click <guibutton>Repositories</guibutton> button again, 
					choose the repository you are about to delete and click 
					<guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-installing-and-updating-extensions">
				<title>Installing and updating extensions</title>

				<para>
					To install an extension click <guibutton>Install extensions...</guibutton> button. 
					In the newly presented dialog
				</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose repository to install from all known repositories or just one of 
							available repositories.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose, what extension packages you want to see: All, Only new, Only updates.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guibutton>Update</guibutton> button to update list of available 
							extension packages by given criteria.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose extensions you want to install/update, click <guibutton>Information</guibutton> 
							to see summary on selected package, if you want to.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to proceed with installation.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-enabling-and-disabling-extensions">
				<title>Enabling and disabling extensions</title>

				<para>
					You might want to temporarily enable or disable a particular extension package, 
					for example, if the extension is not stable enough to handle a large amount of 
					photos or if menus get crowded with extensions.
				</para>
				<para>
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package and click <guibutton>Enable</guibutton> or <guibutton>Disable</guibutton>. 
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-removing-extensions">
				<title>Removing extensions</title>

				<para>
					If you don't need an extension you can remove it from the system completely. 
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package you want to remove and click <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-reading-summary-of-extensions">
				<title>Reading summary of extensions</title>

				<para>
					Every extension package contains metadata that provides the following information about the extension:
				</para>

				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Description, which usually covers puprose of the extension
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Version
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Author
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Dependencies
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				
				<para>
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package you want to read summary of and click <guibutton>Information</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-developing-extensions">
			<title>Developing extensions</title>

			<para>
				<ulink url="http://f-spot.org/Extend_F-Spot">Extend F-Spot</ulink> document 
				gives instructions on developing your own extensions for F-Spot.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="shortcuts">
		<title>Atalhos</title>
		
		<sect1 id="Global-Shortcuts">
			<title>Atalhos Globais</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Tecla</entry>
							<entry>Ação</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>[</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Rotacionar as fotos selecionadas à esquerda</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>]</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Rotacionar as fotos selecionadas à direita</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Del</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Remove selected photos from F-Spot's catalogue
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Del</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Delete selected photos permanently from the drive. If possible, they will moved to trash.
							</entry>
						</row>
 
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>t</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Ver ou editar etiquetas para fotos selecionadas</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F11</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Visualização tela cheia</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Exibir informações sobre a foto</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Igual</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Zoom-in</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Menos</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Zoom-out</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Importar fotos</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>0-5</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Alt plus a number from 0 to 5 rate the selected picture(s)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-browse-mode">
			<title>Atalhos do Modo de Navegação</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Tecla</entry>
							<entry>Ação</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Selecionar todas</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Desmarcar todas</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Arrow keys or <keycap>H</keycap>, <keycap>J</keycap>, 
								<keycap>K</keycap>, <keycap>L</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Mover foco</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-Arrow key
							</entry>
							<entry>Mover o foco sem alterar a seleção</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Barra de espaço</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Selecionar ou desmarcar a foto ativa</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>Arrow key</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Alterar a seleção da foto</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>Left arrow or Right arrow</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Adicionar/Remover todas as fotos na linha, na direção pressionada, para a seleção</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>V</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Abre janela instantânea para uma visualização maior da foto apontada pelo mouse</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Abre janela instantânea para uma visualização maior de um histograma da foto apontada pelo mouse</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-tag">
			<title>Atalhos de Etiquetas</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Tecla</entry>
							<entry>Ação</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Renomear etiqueta selecionada</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>Adicionar etiquetas às fotos selecionadas</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>n/a</entry>
							<entry>Arraste e solte etiquetas para movê-las</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>n/a</entry>
							<entry>Digite o nome da etiqueta para pular até ela (apenas se etiqueta for mostrada/expandida)</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="shortcuts-edit-mode">
			<title>Atalhos do Modo de Edição</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Tecla</entry>
							<entry>Ação</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Up</keycap>, <keycap>Backspace</keycap>, <keycap>B</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Ir para a Foto Anterior</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Down</keycap>, <keycap>Barra de espaço</keycap>, <keycap>N</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Ir para a Foto Seguinte</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Arrow keys or <keycap>H</keycap>, <keycap>J</keycap>, 
								<keycap>K</keycap>, <keycap>L</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Previous/Next photo or move around a zoomed photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>R</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to a random photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>f</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Visualização tela cheia</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>0</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Ajustar a imagem para a tela</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>1</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Fator de Zoom para 1.0 (1 pixel da tela por pixel da imagem)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Fator de Zoom para 2.0 (4 pixels da tela por pixel da imagem)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Escapar</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>Retorna ao modo Navegador</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>V</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Examine photo with magnifying glass (Loupe). Doubleclick on the 
								Loupe, or type <keycap>v</keycap> again to close it.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Shift</keycap>-Mousewheel
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Faster filmstrip scrolling
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>i</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Toggle infobox visibility ''(only when in full screen)''
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

</book>
